Charles Emerson Beecher Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Charles Emerson Beecher Archives
1888-1904
IPAR.001034
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
10
The archives of Charles Emerson Beecher including illustrations, catalogs, notes and locality information encompassing his career at Yale, and focusing on his work with fossil invertebrates.
Beecher, Charles Emerson, 1856-1904
Biographical Sketch
Charles Emerson Beecher (b. 1858, d. 1904), son of Moses and Emily (Emerson) Beecher, was born in Dunkirk, New York, on October 9, 1856. When he was a youth, his family moved to northwestern Pennsylvania and Beecher began collecting fossils from the local sandstones and shales. By the time he arrived at the University of Michigan (B.S. 1878), he had amassed a very respectable collection of fossil phyllocarids and freshwater unionids. Following his graduation from the University of Michigan, Beecher became a personal assistant to James Hall in Albany for 10 years, and then at the request of Yale?s Othniel C. Marsh, he moved to New Haven to oversee the Peabody Museum?s growing collection of invertebrate fossils. In 1891, Beecher was awarded his doctorate for his study on Brachiospongidae, an enigmatic group of Silurian sponges. Although Beecher is best known for his work on trilobites, he really didn?t specialize on any particular group of organisms. Instead, he was interested in biological systems, evolution, and the relationship between ontogeny and phylogeny. Beecher?s promotion was rapid. He ascended to Professor of Historical Geology in 1897 and, on the death of Marsh in 1899, Beecher succeeded him as Curator of the Geological Collections, the informal Director of the Peabody Museum of Natural History.
Description of the Material
Includes drawings, illustrations and photographs of specimens and localities. Also, some correspondence.
Connecticut; New York; USA; Pennsylvania; Maps; Drawings; Locality information; Catalogs; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Drawings, Illustrations, Photographs, 1888-1904; Series I
  - Localities. Photographs and drawings of localities., 001038
    - Photographs. Photograph of Ordovician Beecher Trilobite Bed locality, Cleveland Glen, Rome New York, 000815
  - Specimens. Photographs, Drawingd and illistrations of multiple specimens., 001037
    - Drawing. Scrapbook of original drawings of fossil and Recent invertebrates by C.E. Beecher; donated by Nancy Herzig (relative of Beecher) in Sept. 2005, 1882; 000814
    - Drawing. Original drawings, 1893, 1894, 1895, 1920: bl. & wh. photographs & glass negatives for papers on trilobite appendages; Triarthrus becki, Cryptolithus & Acidaspis; reprints of Pl. 8 of Beecher, 1896; list of people & institutions to whom Triarthrus-legged specimens were sent; total material rec'd. 20 boxes, 34 barrels, & 4 small lots., 000755
    - Drawing. Original illustrations for C.E. Beecher, 1902, Revision of the Phyllocaridae from the Chemung Formation (R.0119): Pennsylvania., 000267
    - Drawing. Original drawings of trilobite ontogeny (including Triarthrus) and trilobite cephala., 2002; 000756
    - Photographs. Two 4x5 black and white prints and one 4x5 glass negative of the actual specimen YPM 26319, Prestwichia signata Beecher. 4x5 black and white print & 4x5 negative, 000554
    - photographs. Drawings, illustrations & photographs of Brachiospongia: Kentucky, Tennessee., 1889; 000276
- Miscellaneous, 1888-1904; Series II
  - Correspondence. Correspondense to and from Charles E. Beecher., 001040
    - Papers, notes, correspondence. Letters to his wife from Charles Beecher and a letter from James Dana to Beecher; donated by Nancy Herzig (relative of Beecher) in Sept. 2005, 000952
  - Locality Information. Locality information including notes and maps., 001039
    - Divisional notes. Locality information on "Beecher's Trilobite Bed": Ordovician, Utica Sh, New York. 2 different maps by Fred Collier of Smithsonian and by John S. Koziarz, 7922 Smith Rd., Rome, NY tel. (315)-865-4281 (current owner, 2003). Beecher's lease deed with G. Cleveland. Bio. info. on W.S. Valiant & F.L. Nason, and reprint by Valiant., 1989; 000265
    - Locality information. locality information., 1892; 000499
    - Locality information. Locality information, Maine., 1892; 000656
    - Location map. Recent quadrangle xeroxes of Jerusalem Hill area: New York., 1901; 000349
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous Archives including divisional notes., 001042
    - Divisional notes. Note on disposition of Beecher's Trilobite Bed material: New York., 1988; 000227
  - Specimen Lists. Catalogs of specimen identifications., 001041
    - Catalog of identifications. Catalog of Waverly Group fossil plants, Pennsylvania; and mostly living and a few fossil invertebrates., 1872; 000216
    - Catalog of identifications. Catalog of invertebrate fossils: New York, Pennsylvania, & few Ohio, Missouri, Kansas, Michigan; red ink on light blue-gray paint., 1887; 000217